Finding Aid for Carol H. Tice papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carol H. Tice Papers 1970-2012 1970-2000
Tice, Carol H.
8.5 linear feet (in 9 boxes), 1 oversize box, 1 oversize folder, and 2.31 GB (online)
2014145 Aa 2 UAl
Art teacher in Ann Arbor, Mich. Public schools and the founder of the Teaching-Learning Communities program and Lifespan Resources, Inc., an educational non-profit organization. Administrative papers, correspondence, news clippings, photographs, reports, grant proposals, and personal speeches and publications related to intergenerational education and related initiatives from the early 1970s until 2000.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Carol Tice (Donor no. 11028 ) in November 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Carol H. Tice was born in 1931 and received a B.S. from Manchester College in 1954 and an M.Ed. from Cornell University in 1955. She taught several grades at a few different schools in Princeton, New Jersey before moving coming to Ann Arbor, Michigan to teach elementary art.
While teaching, Tice started the Teaching-Learning Communities (T-LC) program in Ann Arbor Public schools in 1971. This intergenerational initiative brought volunteer "grandpersons," senior citizens who volunteered as mentors, into the classroom where they worked with students on creative skills, such as handicrafts or cooking. In this way, T-LC gave students an opportunity to learn from their elders and the elders an opportunity to stay active in the community. The goal was to unite two generations that might not otherwise interact, fostering greater mutual understanding and respect among different generations.
Tice served as director of T-LC until 2000, during which time she continued to teach and pursue other professional activities. In 1979, she founded a non-profit organization called New Age, Inc. (which changed its name to Lifespan Resources, Inc. in the early 1980s) to support T-LC and other similar intergenerational initiatives in schools. Lifespan provided resources for the adoption of intergenerational programs modeled on T-LC in other locations, including Chicago, Detroit, and Atlanta. Tice supported this work by publishing and speaking at conferences around the country. She also participated in various larger projects such as the International year of the Child and as a consultant for the U.S. Senate Special Committee on Aging.
After retiring from Ann Arbor Public Schools in 2000, Tice continued to operate Lifespan Resources, Inc. in a smaller capacity and also volunteered with other projects in the community.
The collection is arranged into three series representing Tice's personal and professional work: Teaching-Learning Communities Records, Lifespan Resources, Inc. Records, and Personal Materials.
The personal papers of Carol Tice document her contributions to the development of intergenerational education in the Ann Arbor Public Schools and the Ann Arbor Community more broadly.
Subjects:
Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Intergenerational relations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Lifespan Resources, Inc.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Tice, Carol H.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Older people--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; School children--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Digital moving image formats.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Teaching-Learning Communities Records
  The Teaching-Learning Communities Records series (1971-2012, 5.5 linear feet plus one oversize box and one oversize folder) consists of materials related to the T-LC program created by Tice and others. This includes administrative materials such as budgets, planning and volunteer records as well as correspondence. Additionally are event records from a visit by Margaret Mead and a concert by Eva Jessye, as well as curricular materials created by T-LC and Lifespan Resources, Inc. such as guidebooks, training materials, and worksheets used by volunteers and teachers. Finally some student work is included along and informational materials such as photographs of students and volunteers, newspaper clippings about T-LC, brochures, posters, and scrapbooks.
  - Administrative Materials, 1974-2012, 85 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980-2006, 60 folders (Box 2)
  - Events
    - Eva Jessye Concert, 1978, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Margaret Mead Visit
      - Related materials 1976, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Interview (Carol Tice and Margaret Mead), 1976, .MP4 and .ZIP files
  - Curricular Materials
    - 1971-1988, 38 folders and 1 VHS videocassette (Box 3)
    - 1991-2006, 15 folders and 9 volumes (Box 4)
  - Informational materials (Box 5)
    - 1970-1992, 87 folders (Box 5)
    - 1993-2000, 33 folders (Box 6)
    - 19700-2000 (Box 10)
    - circa 1980 (Folder 1)
- Lifespan Resources, Inc. Records ,1973-2007
  The Lifespan Resources, Inc. Records series (1973-2007, 2.5 linear feet) consists of materials created by Lifespan that were not related to T-LC. This includes reports on existing Lifespan programs and similar programs elsewhere, and grant proposals for future programs with which Tice was involved, some of which was the implementation of intergenerational education programs in other cities including Atlanta and Chicago. Additionally there are papers from related projects about intergenerational education in which Tice was involved including International Year of the Child and a film called "What We Have" in which T-LC is featured. Finally there are reference materials, in which Lifespan was listed by outside organizations as resource in intergenerational education.
  - Reports and proposals
    - 1973-1976, 14 folders (Box 6)
    - 1977-2007, 55 folders (Box 7)
  - Related Projects, 1974-1994, 26 folders (Box 8)
  - Reference Materials, 1979-2004, 15 folders (Box 8)
  - What We Have, 1982, .MP4 and .ZIP files; (Film about intergenerational learning, produced by the University of Michigan Film Unit)
- Personal Materials, 1979-2001
  The Personal Materials series, (1979-2001, 0.5 linear feet) includes speeches and articles written by Tice, as well as awards and biographical material, and a small amount of material related to other professional activities, including her involvement with Blue Lake Fine Arts Camp.
  - 1979-2001, 20 folders (Box 9)
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library holds the Ann Arbor Public Schools records. There are three folders in the "Administration, 1946-1991" series with materials related to Teaching Learning Communities from 1974-1976.